Guide to the Smith-Nyman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Smith-Nyman papers
1929-1953
1929-1939
MS 456
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.75
(12 boxes)
Reports, case studies, and background material used in research on a group of textile mills, primarily in the Southern United States, which had introduced the "textile stretch-out" or extended "labor system." Some of this research was sponsored by the Institute of Human Relations and was undertaken jointly with Richmond Carter Nyman.
Smith, Elliott Dunlap, 1891-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elliott Dunlap and Richmond C. Nyman in 1939, 1940, 1944, and 1963.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Elliott Dunlap Smith: B.A. Harvard 1913, LL.B., 1916; Professor Industrial Engineering, Yale, 1928-1932, Professor Industrial Relations, 1932-1938, Professor Economics, 1938-1946, asst. to the President, 1942-1943.
Richmond Carter Nyman: research asst., industrial engineering, Yale, 1930-1934, industrial relations, 1934-1937, Personnel Director, 1939-1951, asst. Secretary of University, 1940-1941.
Scope and Contents
Reports, case studies, and background material used in research on a group of textile mills, primarily in the Southern United States, which had introduced the "textile stretch-out" or extended "labor system." Some of this research was sponsored by the Institute of Human Relations and was undertaken jointly with Richmond Carter Nyman.
Industrial engineering; Industrial relations; Working class; Textile industry; Southern States -- Economic conditions; Labor movement; Labor; Nyman, Richmond Carter, 1900-; Smith, Elliott Dunlap, 1891-
- Inventory
  - General materials: reports, research material, correspondence
    - "Introduction to Multiple Loom (Stretch-Out) Syster; General and Historical Background": Vol. I, undated (Box 1)
    - "Smith-Nyman Textile Stretch-Out Study": Vols. I-II, 1931-1937, undated (Box 1)
    - "British Stretch-Out (More Looms) System": Vols I-III, 1932, 1934, undated (Box 2)
    - "Case Study Summaries—Worker Extension in the Cotton Textile Industry", 1932 (Box 2)
    - "Industrial Relations in Great Britain", 1939 (Box 2)
    - "Industrial Relations in Sweden", 1939 (Box 2)
    - "Higher Education and Industrial Productivity in Norway", 1953 (Box 2)
    - Year Book of the Dept. of Agricutlture, Commerce and Industries of the State of South Carolina, 1929 (Box 2)
    - Harvard Business Review, 1930 (Box 2)
  - "Regulation of the 'Stretch-Out' by the national Recovery Administration, June 1933-Feb1935": reports, correspondence, notes, printed matter, 1933-1935 (Box 2)
    - Vols. 1-4 (Box 3)
    - Vols. 4A-10 (Box 4)
  - Case studies: reports, correspondence, notes, printed matter, photographs, Circa 1929-1939 (Box 4)
    - 1: Pacific Mills, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 5)
    - 2: Pacific Mills, Hampton Division, Columbia, S.C. (Box 5)
    - 3: Thrift Mill, Kendall Co., Paw Creek, N.C. (Box 5)
    - 4: Exposition Cotton Mills, Atlanta, Ga. (Box 6)
    - 5: Anniston Manufacturing Co., Anniston, Ala. (Box 6)
    - 6: Pequot Mills, Naumkeag Steam Cotton Co., Salem, Mass. (Box 7)
    - 6: Pequot Mills, Naumkeag Steam Cotton Co., Salem, Mass. (Box 8)
    - 6: Pequot Mills, Naumkeag Steam Cotton Co., Salem, Mass. (Box 9)
    - 7: Buffalo Mill, Union-Buffalo Mills Co., Buffalo, S.C. (Box 9)
    - 8: Pepperell Mills, Pepperell Manufacturing Co., Biddeford, Me., and Lindale, Ga. (Box 10)
    - 10: "Confederate Mills," Danville, Va. (Box 10)
    - 10: "Confederate Mills," Danville, Va. (Box 11)
    - 11: Ware Shoals Manufacturing Co., Ware Shoals, S.C. (Box 11)
    - 13: Wearwell Weaving Mill, Carolina Cotton and Woolen Mills Co., Draper, N.C. (Box 11)
    - "Communism and the 'stretch-out' Case Report by R.C. Nyman, " Add. March 9, 1984, 1936 (Box 12)